<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Grumpy Learning]]></title>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/"/>
    <updated>2024-12-27T15:33:30+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/</id>
    <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes -- November 22, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/11/22/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/11/22/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back on the notes grind...</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>ZiffDavis Shopping is getting close to our Super Bowl -- Black Friday and Cyber Monday</li>
<li>wrote a PHP CLI tool that will mimic an existing Python job and emit events for updating reward budgets as we pay folks out</li>
<li>diving deeper into Laravel Nova actions and creating code for doing CSV exports of selected Eloquent models</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I got asked a question on social media about how to handle things when you
come onto a team as Staff-level engineer and getting them
to commit to making things more maintainable.</p>

<p>I could do a whole talk about this, but let me summarize a few points.</p>

<p>1) talk to the people YOU report TO and get expectations on quality and output
2) ruthlessly enforce those expectations with your team
3) make team understand they are building new habits while delivering what the business wants
4) the path to maintainable code is through being able to write tests for it</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Abridged Story of TrueNorth PHP]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/11/04/true-north-php/"/>
            <updated>2024-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/11/04/true-north-php/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am going to try and write this article without doing a lot of back-and-forth
and editing. TrueNorth PHP was a PHP-centric developer conference that
Pete Meth and myself ran from 2012-2016. Five events. Awesome speakers.
Even more awesome attendees.</p>

<p>For me this was the golden age of PHP conferences.</p>

<p>Any mistakes in here are mine and mine alone -- a lot the background stuff
happened 13 or 14 years ago. Sometimes I cannot remember what I had
for breakfast.</p>

<h3 id="%22i-want-to-do-a-conference%22">"I want to do a conference"</h3>

<p>Ironically it wasn't me who first made this suggestion. One of our GTA
area developers who used to come out to the GTA PHP User Group mentioned
to me that he wanted to do a travelling conference -- going from location
to location here in Ontario.</p>

<p>While I liked the idea of another event I didn't want to have it be
a travelling one -- mainly because it was unlikely I could get the necessary
time off to go to all those locations!</p>

<p>So, I talked to Pete (who was helping me run the user group at the time)
and he was in.</p>

<h3 id="%22can-i-get-some-advice%3F%22">"Can I get some advice?"</h3>

<p>My next move was to talk to Marco Tabini (who helped start php|architect
and ran a conference for many years) to get some high-level advice. We
met for coffee somewhere north of Toronto. As I remember, here is what
he said:</p>

<ul>
<li>keep it small</li>
<li>find a date nobody else is using</li>
<li>getting sponsors will be the hardest part</li>
</ul>

<p>All great advice. So I decided November was good (venues tended to be
cheaper) and that the best way to split things up was for me to be the
hype man and speaker handler while Pete handled everything else.</p>

<h3 id="%22everything-went-so-well%21%22">"Everything went so well!"</h3>

<p>We definitely lucked into have Microsoft Canada's offices not far from
the Toronto airport being a perfect venue:</p>

<ul>
<li>three rooms</li>
<li>great A/V support</li>
<li>on-site catering</li>
</ul>

<p>I can honestly say that we did not have any major problems at any of
the five events we ran. From my years of being on the speaking circuit
I had no shortage of friends I could ask to come speak along with
always getting a large number of quality submissions every time.</p>

<p>I don't think it could've gone any better.</p>

<p>Running a conference is hard. Ask any organizer. For one to go so
well is astonishing. We could've kept doing it for a long long time.</p>

<p>I treated the speakers the way I wanted to be treated by events. The
staff at the venue were incredibly supportive.</p>

<p>Five years of a great event that people started lamenting they couldn't
make it to was awesome</p>

<h3 id="%22i-think-we-should-do-this-one-last-time%22">"I think we should do this one last time"</h3>

<p>After each event Pete and I would have dinner the next day and talk about
how it went. Each time we did it, there were less and less unexpected things.
I said to him after the 4th one -- "are you getting bored of doing this?"
He replied that he was so we agreed that we would do it one last time.</p>

<h3 id="%22pete%2C-we-did-it%21%22">"Pete, we did it!"</h3>

<p>I always did the closing talk of the event and when it came for my last
time, it was emotional. I reflected on what we had accomplished with
just two organizers and a lot of enthusiastic volunteers.</p>

<p>Pete and I drifted apart without the common event to unite us but we
did stay in touch and on those occasions we were together it felt like
no time had passed.</p>

<h3 id="thank-you">Thank You</h3>

<p>If you attended any of these events -- thank you for supporting an idea
that got turned into reality.</p>

<p>If you spoke at any of these events -- thank you for taking the time to
hang out with me and make the lives of the attendees a little better.</p>

<p>If you missed out -- I don't know what to tell you other than I'm
sorry it didn't work out for you.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Surviving conferences as a speaker]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/29/surviving-as-a-speaker/"/>
            <updated>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/29/surviving-as-a-speaker/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just got back from speaking at <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">CascadiaPHP</a>
and wanted to share some thoughts about how I approach going to conferences
as a speaker and maybe you will find it helpful too.</p>

<h3 id="you-are-playing-a-dual-role">You are playing a dual role</h3>

<p>I have been going to conferences since 2003 and speaking at them since 2005.
That is a very long time, spanning the vast majority of my professional
career. Most of my energy and attention are devoted to making sure that
I deliver the best talk I can at the time I give it.</p>

<p>I also need to show other attendees that I still have things to learn so
I make sure to go to other talks.</p>

<p>I understand that for some folks time pressures are such that they come in,
give a talk, and then immediately leave. I am not a fan of that approach and
would never do it -- I would just simply decline the opportunity. But for
many events they are marketed as an opportunity to get access to some of
the most knowledgeable people in your programming community. So I feel
you should give back by making sure to talk to other people, make some
new community friends, and encourage people to continue to attend these
events.</p>

<p>So make sure to support your other speakers by attending their talks. I
know I missed some talks at CascadiaPHP because I was not handling
the 3-hour time difference well and I was catching up with some old friends
during other talks. I did get to some talks of things I was interested in
and that is really what we are here for.</p>

<h3 id="know-your-material">Know your material</h3>

<p>I will admit that I often don't practice my talks because I make sure I
really know the material before I present. I think I can mostly get away
with this because of my presentation style -- it is kind of like walking
a tightrope.</p>

<p>So even if you can't practice your talk a lot, if you understand the
material really well then a collection of slides that act as the initial
thoughts you want to go over, and then you fill in the rest yourself
makes for really engaging talks.</p>

<h3 id="answer-questions-and-ask-questions">Answer questions and ask questions</h3>

<p>This can be hard for people who suffer from "imposter syndrome". My joke
about this is that my ego is too large for me to think I am an imposter,
but the truth is I am highly confident that I can figure out how to do
just about anything. The key to pulling that off is to understand when
you don't know something and then figure out who you can ask for help.</p>

<p>In the context of a conference, I try to do talks that question the
way some things are, present my point of view, and then ask the audience
to consider what I've told them. You don't have to agree with everything
I say (talks that like that are boring) but I do actually change my mind
over time and with experience. So try and get your audience thinking
and wanting to ask questions.</p>

<p>Conversely, if you are watching someone else's talk and don't understand
what is going on, ask them a question if you can. I generally ask people
to save their questions for the end of my talks but feel free to go with
whatever feels right for you.</p>

<p>A great example of this is the topic of <a href="https://phpstan.org/blog/generics-by-examples">generics in PHP</a>. I have never
used them and have not been able to figure out on my own why they might
be useful to me. There was a talk about <a href="https://phpstan.org">PHPStan</a>
and they mentioned generics. I didn't ask the speaker about them as
I got to the end so instead I asked some of my fellow developers if
they could explain to me why I should care about them. They provided
me with some insights into when and where I might want to use them
so next time I am building something that could benefit from Generics,
I will give it a try.</p>

<p>If I hadn't asked, a question I probably would still be thinking they were something
I would not have to worry about.</p>

<h3 id="take-care-of-yourself">Take care of yourself</h3>

<p>Make sure to eat.</p>

<p>Make sure to get proper amounts of rest.</p>

<p>Don't treat the conference like it's an excuse to cut loose and abuse yourself.</p>

<p>I don't want to say things like "be a professional" because that on it's own
is really insulting. Instead, be respectful towards yourself.</p>

<h3 id="have-your-slides-done-ahead-of-time">Have your slides done ahead of time</h3>

<p>There is the trope of folks doing their slides at the last minute. In almost
every case I have my slides all done before I come to the event, This time
I ended up needing to devote the time I would've spent on slides for one
of my presentations doing stuff around my house getting it ready to be sold.
I ended up finishing the slides in my hotel room during a block of talks
that I did not find interesting enough to attend.</p>

<h3 id="sometimes-the-talk-just-doesn%27t-work">Sometimes the talk just doesn't work</h3>

<p>This final one is tricky. Sometimes, a talk just doesn't resonate with the
audience. You miscalculated how much time you had. You wanted to talk theory
but the audience was expecting examples. You only prepared 30 minutes when
the slot was an hour. It was the first time you gave the talk. It happens.
I view them as teachable lessons about what the audience is expecting from
you, which becomes even more important if you are lucky enough to have
a long enough speaking career where there are expectations that you are
going to be a certain way.</p>

<p>We can all learn from our challenges -- failing to do so is the real issue.</p>

<h3 id="you-made-it%21">You made it!</h3>

<p>If you want to an event and spoke, congratulations! Now try and make the
experience for your audience and yourself just a little bit better next time.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes October 18th, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/18/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/18/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>work has changed to be using scrum...not a fan</li>
<li>learned about how we need to change how we are doing <code>count()</code> queries in <a href="https://nova.laravel.com">Laravel Nova</a></li>
<li>work swtiched from Docker Desktop to <a href="https://podman.io">Podman</a> to avoid the enterprise fees</li>
<li>as we get closer and closer to launching my new transaction processing work, getting into the fringes of triggering events and reacting to them</li>
<li>one talk written and one more to go for <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">CascadiaPHP</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>Is it possible to both be excited and filled with dread at buying a house and moving? We found
a place in the small town where we live (literally a 5 minute drive) and buying
it is conditional on selling our current place in a very tight window (about 5
weeks).</p>

<p>I'm pretty organized these days so the move will likely go smooth but I am going
to spend all winter in a foul move if it falls through.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes October 4th, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/04/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/04/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>See, already got lazy about this. Distracted by stuff
at home and my annual visit to go see the Tigers play
at Comerica Field the last weekend they are at home.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>the IBL regular season is almost over -- 2 weeks to go and my team sits at 73-73</li>
<li>got a foul ball at the Tigers' game -- I whiffed on catching it but it hit me in the gut and dropped to my feet. Awesome souvenir for my buddy's 10yo son</li>
<li>two weeks of fun Commander play, with 20 people coming out each time</li>
<li>finally getting some time to work on my Magic: The Gathering <a href="https://cubecobra.com/cube/overview/grumpycursed">cube</a></li>
<li>some of the last pieces of my work task related to purchase validation are getting built</li>
<li>demo of some other features built by the rest of the team went well</li>
<li>pool is now closed as we settle in for a Southwestern Ontario fall</li>
<li>started working on my slides for my two talks at <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">CascadiaPHP 2024</a></li>
<li>house hunting has started as we look for something without a pool (I'm the only one really using it, plus with our youngest having epilepsy there is significant risk to her swimming) and move from a two-story home to a bungalow</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>Nothing really other than my absences from home make me realize what
a creature of routine I have become over the years. Even an overnight
visit feels like it was super long. Weird sensation for sure.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes September 13th, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/13/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/13/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Shout out to <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason_Voorhees">Jason Voorhees</a>
on his special day.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>no IBL games this week as we had a real week off -- will be playing some games this upcoming Sunday</li>
<li>amazing turnout for Commander night -- 24 people</li>
<li>put my favourite deck back together (<a href="https://archidekt.com/decks/9190742/grolnok_v3">Grolnok Turbo Self-Mill</a> and remembered how that deck quickly becomes the archenemy of the table as it is fast and consistent</li>
<li>finally got my transaction audit work merged into the main branch at work</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>This upcoming Monday I am going to a meeting with my mother
at the nursing home where my father lives to go over his
care. Some of you might know that my father is suffering 
from dementia for about a decade now and has been in
this home for 2-1/2 years now.</p>

<p>I try and see him whenever I go back to visit my mom and
for the most part the visits have gone okay. He seems to
almost always remember that he has a son and the last
few visits he always recognizes my mother. Conversations
are hard because he doesn't remember anything and I don't
have enough things on my phone to really distract him. My
mother often brings an iPad with her and shows him videos
or pictures of things.</p>

<p>The whole thing is really, really sad. I have no idea if
I will dodge the same fate as him.</p>

<p>I think the thing that bothers me the most is that while
he looks like and sounds like my Dad, it's not. He never
remembers I have kids or that I am married. I haven't
heard him talk about my older sister at all.</p>

<p>I just wish he was able to experience that his son truly
made it and has a nice comfortable life.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes September 7th, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/07/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/07/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games</li>
<li>has my usual Commander Night at my local gaming store</li>
<li>the transaction audit log work is proving to be a slog</li>
<li>discovered that you can configure PhpStorm's <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/help/phpstorm/using-product-as-the-vim-editor.html">IdeaVim</a> plugin via a <code>.ideavimrc</code> file to make the experience a little more Vim-like. Shoutout to Eric Johnson from <a href="https://www.phparch.com">php|architect</a> for showing me how</li>
<li>flights booked for going to <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">CascadiaPHP</a> at the end of October</li>
<li>a testing scenario for the transaction audit log revealed that my <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chain-of-responsibility_pattern">chain-of-responsibility</a> implementation for a series of validators for a rebate offer was just wrong, so off I went fixing it by switching to using <a href="https://laravel.com/docs/11.x/helpers#pipeline">pipelines in laravel</a>. Don't worry, all the individual validators have tests</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I was going to do a longer piece on how I felt I was at
a "crossroads" with my IDE choices. I know it sounds like
dramatic whining.</p>

<p>I have been a Vim/NeoVim user for a long time. The HJKL
muscle memory is burned in and I expect almost everything
I use to be modal. For everything other than PHP, I use
NeoVim.</p>

<p>But lately I am feeling...resentful about how all the tools
I have started to rely on seem to have "becoming a subscription"
as an aspirational goal. My renewal for my PhpStorm subscription
is coming up and I am trying to decide if I can just not renew
it and go back to NeoVim.</p>

<p>The ONLY reason I switched to using PhpStorm was because it
made some other aspects of development work easier:</p>

<ul>
<li>easily get Xdebug working and a slick interface for it</li>
<li>same with doing development work with Dockerized development environments</li>
<li>make it easy to run my tests inside that Dockerized environments</li>
<li>"intellesense" support baked in</li>
</ul>

<p>There are other editors I have looked at -- <a href="https://helix-editor.com">Helix</a>,
<a href="https://zed.dev">Zed</a>, and even the dreaded Emacs. Other than Emacs,
the newer editors fall down when we get to the plugin and
customization phage of creating a development environment.</p>

<p>From a pragmatic side, sticking with NeoVim due to intimate 
familiarity with it's modal nature and basic keybindings
makes the most sense.</p>

<p>Emacs is an interesting choice because it is basically like
NeoVim in that it has a long, rich history and is incredibly
configurable. But learning a whole new series of keybindings?
Seems very daunting.</p>

<p>Helix seems nice. Xdebug support appears to be very rough to
get working. Have to have it for my PHP work, sorry. No idea
if it can be made to support Xdebug running inside a Docker
container. Again, need to check back later.</p>

<p>Zed -- no support for Xdebug. I'll check back later when
they maybe bake in Debug Anywhere Protocol support.</p>

<p>So time to see if I can get NeoVim to give me the extra
tooling that PhpStorm currently offers.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes September 1st, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/01/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/01/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games, where we continue to hover around the .500 mark</li>
<li>double dose of Magic: The Gathering this week -- played both my <a href="https://cubecobra.com/cube/overview/grumpycursed">cursed cube</a> and <a href="https://pdhhomebase.com">pauper commander</a></li>
<li>implemented some transaction audit logging at work -- test cases as expected</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I read an excelled blog post from Steven Yegge where he talked about how
he felt it was a <a href="https://sourcegraph.com/blog/the-death-of-the-junior-developer?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email">bad time to be a junior developer</a>,
which dovetails nicely into me needing to deliver a talk at the end
of October to the audience at <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">Cascadia PHP</a>
about how a hater like me uses LLM's.</p>

<p>I don't want to spoil the main points of the talk, but it is fair
to say I already use some LLM's (Apple iPhone already has stuff
in it) and I have occasionally turned it on when trying to refactor
some code.</p>

<p>Can't ignore all the grifters and rent-seekers hanging around
the industry and it does feel like a bubble is gonna pop.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes August 25, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/25/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/25/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A little late this week.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games, where we continue to hover around the .500 mark</li>
<li>did a lot of work with <a href="https://nova.laravel.com">Nova</a> to build a dashboard for auditing transactions as they flow through our verification system</li>
<li>a fun Thursday of Magic: The Gathering playing commander</li>
<li>stomach still not great</li>
<li>played Doomlings and our 6+ year <a href="http://www.apocalypse-world.com">Apocalypse World</a> game</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I tried out Emacs this week at work for a little bit each
day and it is just different enough from what my Vim
muscle memory wants that I have put it on hold.</p>

<p>Instead, I am concentrating on building new muscle memory
to use <a href="https://precondition.github.io/home-row-mods">home row mods</a>
to reduce how often I have to reach for the Shift and Alt keys.
It's jarring to actually feel the pause as I stop to use the
home row "shift".</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
                    <author>
                <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                            </author>
                    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes August 16, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/16/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/16/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games via instructions (team managers create documents for how they want their team to be run)</li>
<li>finished writing all the tests for additional scenarios for the transaction processing job</li>
<li>no Magic: The Gathering this week as Commander night was my 26th wedding anniversary</li>
<li>stomach is feeling a little better -- I wonder if the ache I feel is because of damage all that stomach acid has done :(</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I came across a blog post from a developer about <a href="https://protesilaos.com/codelog/2019-08-11-why-emacs-switch/">why they switched to Emacs</a>
and it make me wonder if I should try switching from Vim to Emacs. Again.</p>

<p>I tried it once before but couldn't duplicate my developer work flow.
I feel like the combination of <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a> + <a href="http://xahlee.info/emacs/misc/xah-fly-keys.html">xah-fly-keys</a> is
a great start since it would give me a similar modal editing experience
that I expect in my editor.</p>

<p>Of course, the bigger issue is that I would have to set things up twice
-- once on my work computer that ZiffDavis gave me and once on my own
machine. I also pay for a license for <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">PhpStorm</a>
and it is up for renewal soon.</p>

<p>Good to keep learning things. I've been using Vim so long that navigating via H-J-K-L
is deeply embedded in muscle memory. I have noticed over the years that I don't really
do much "web surfing" on my laptop -- I use my iPhone for that so having Vim bindings
for my browser doesn't make mush sense.</p>

<h2 id="everything-else">Everything Else</h2>

<ul>
<li>going to be playing <a href="https://doomlings.com">Doomlings</a> this weekend as part of my monthly board gaming session</li>
<li>if you are interested in ergonomic keyboards I would check out the Glove80 from <a href="https://www.moergo.com">moergo</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>