<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Grumpy Learning]]></title>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/categories/indieweb.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/"/>
    <updated>2024-07-20T11:59:10+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Grumpy POSSE]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2022/11/18/a-grumpy-posse/"/>
            <updated>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2022/11/18/a-grumpy-posse/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the main reasons I have decided to embrace more of
the <a href="https://indieweb.org">IndieWeb</a> ethos is out of a desire
to have more control over where the various things I create
(micro-blogging and longer-form content) ends up. Twitter ended
up being something that replaced the blogging I used to do.</p>

<p>One of the concepts coming out of the Indieweb is the great-sounding
acronym POSSE. It stands for Publish On your own Site, Syndicate Elsewhere.
Which is another way of saying you should have one central location
where most of your material lives (shitposting on social media still will
happen) and then push that content out to other places.</p>

<p>So for me, what would this look like?</p>

<p>For a long time I had another blog, but once I really leaned into the
Grumpy Programmer brand that blog served no purpose and I really should've
just moved stuff over there. Although that old blog is no longer online
I still have all the posts I made to it. Maybe I will go through one day
and do "the best of when I was less grumpy" or something like that.</p>

<p>So, in a world where I embrace POSSE, here is how it should work:</p>

<ul>
<li>I write content on this blog</li>
<li>I use the static site generator <a href="https://sculpin.io">Sculpin</a> to create the site</li>
<li>As part of updating my site, I then automatically publish a link to that blog elsewhere</li>
</ul>

<p>There are other solutions to make this happen if you use other blogging
engines (static or otherwise) but there was nothing out-of-the-box to make it
work for Sculpin. So, I used my <a href="https://duckduckgo.com">favourite search engine</a>
and started doing some research.</p>

<p>I also, like any good online influencer, leveraged my personal relationships
with people...like the current maintainer of Sculpin...to ask them how I could accomplish
a few tasks.</p>

<h2 id="writing-on-this-blog">Writing on this blog</h2>

<p>Sculpin supports me writing posts using Markdown. This means I get to keep using
the <a href="https://neovim.io">new One True Editor</a> to create new posts. It also uses
<a href="https://twig.symfony.com">Twig</a> for the templates it uses to generate the static
HTML for the site.</p>

<p>Again, I am not telling you one way or the other what to use for your blog. For a lot
of folks using <a href="https://wordpress.com">Wordpress</a> and a plugin tailored to IndieWeb
needs will work. I didn't want to setup anything new, so I was going to stick with
Sculpin.</p>

<h2 id="creating-the-site">Creating the site</h2>

<p>I am currently using GitHub pages for this site, so all I have to do is copy the
generated HTML output into the correct location in the repo that holds my site,
push those changes up to GitHub and in a minute or two I have a new version of
my web site for all the world to see.</p>

<p>This is no big change for what I was doing previously -- I used to have an AWS
Lightsail instance for hosting the blog but decided GitHub was a better option
since I was already paying for an account there. Why pay twice?!?</p>

<p>Now, to prepare my site to be "IndieWeb friendly" is simply followed the instructions
at <a href="https://indiewebify.me">IndeWebify.me</a>. Followed by, of course, a lot of
commits and pushes to get things to behave exactly the way I needed them to.</p>

<p>For example. this is what the template looks like for a blog post, with all the
IndieWeb <a href="https://microformats.org/">microformats</a> embedded in them:</p>

<pre><code>
{% extends "default" %}

{% block head_meta %}
    &lt;meta name="robots" content="index, follow"&gt;
{% endblock %}

{% block content_wrapper %}
    &lt;article class="h-entry"&gt;
        &lt;header&gt;
            &lt;h2&gt;&lt;div class="p-name"&gt;{{ page.title }}&lt;/div&gt; &lt;small&gt;post&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;/header&gt;
        &lt;div class="e-content"&gt;
            {{ page.blocks.content|raw }}
        &lt;/div&gt;
        {% if page.categories %}
            &lt;p class="categories"&gt;
            Categories:
            {% for category in page.categories %}
            &lt;a class="p-category" href="{{ site.url }}/blog/categories/{{ category|url_encode(true) }}"&gt;{{ category }}&lt;/a&gt;{% if not loop.last %}, {% endif %}
            {% endfor %}
            &lt;/p&gt;
        {% endif %}
        {% if page.tags %}
            &lt;p class="tags"&gt;
            Tags:
            {% for tag in page.tags %}
            &lt;a href="{{ site.url }}/blog/tags/{{ tag|url_encode(true) }}"&gt;{{ tag }}&lt;/a&gt;{% if not loop.last %}, {% endif %}
            {% endfor %}
            &lt;/p&gt;
        {% endif %}
        &lt;a href="https://brid.gy/publish/mastodon"&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;a href="https://brid.gy/publish/twitter"&lt;/a&gt;
        {% if page.previous_post or page.next_post %}
            &lt;nav class="article"&gt;
                &lt;ul&gt;
                    {% if page.next_post %}
                        &lt;li&gt;Next: &lt;a class="next" href="{{ site.url }}{{ page.next_post.url }}" title="{{ page.next_post.title }}"&gt;&lt;span class="title"&gt;{{ page.next_post.title }}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    {% endif %}
                    {% if page.previous_post %}
                        &lt;li&gt;Previous: &lt;a class="previous" href="{{ site.url }}{{ page.previous_post.url }}" title="{{ page.previous_post.title }}"&gt;&lt;span class="title"&gt;{{ page.previous_post.title }}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    {% endif %}
                &lt;/ul&gt;
            &lt;/nav&gt;
        {% endif %}
    &lt;/article&gt;
{% endblock %}

</code></pre>

<h2 id="the-grumpy-posse">The Grumpy POSSE</h2>

<p>Figuring out how to syndicate my content without an existing plugin proved to
be a bit of a challenge. Luckily, I found a blog post that explained how to
make this work by embracing <a href="https://indieweb.org/Webmention">Webmentions</a>
and using an awesome (and free!) service called <a href="https://brid.gy">Bridgy</a>
to automate syndication.</p>

<p>The solution I found was to create a GitHub action that would be triggered
each time I did a push to the repo. This action would take care of using
webmentions and Brid.gy to do the magic. But first, I needed a feed of
my website that was in JSON, not XML.</p>

<p>So I hit up <a href="https://phpc.social/@kboyd">Kevin Boyd</a> and ask him how
could I do this in Sculpin. He very gracious created a Twig template
that would turn my list of blog posts into a JSON feed. Here it is
in all it's glory:</p>

<pre><code>
---
permalink: feed.json
use:
    - posts
---
{#
     Example data structure for delivering a Webmentions feed:

     From: https://blog.geheimesite.nl/en/index.json

     [
        {
            "author": {},
            "categories": ,
            "content": "yadda yadda yadda",
            "date": "2022-05-03T16:27:18+02:0",
            "site": "https://whateverthing.com/",
            "tags": null,
            "title": "Article One",
            "uri": "https://whateverthing.com/2022/11/11/article-one/"
        },
        {
            "author": {},
            "categories": ,
            "content": "yadda yadda yadda",
            "date": "2022-06-03T16:27:18+02:0",
            "site": "https://whateverthing.com/",
            "tags": null,
            "title": "Article Two",
            "uri": "https://whateverthing.com/2022/11/11/article-two/"
        },
     ]
#}
{% set outputArray = [] %}

{% for post in data.posts[:10] %}
    {%
        set postOutput = {
            'author': site.author,
            'categories': post.meta.categories,
            'content': post.blocks.content|raw,
            'date': post.date|date("c"),
            'site': site.global_url,
            'tags': post.meta.tags,
            'title': post.title,
            'uri': [ site.global_url, post.url]|join
        }
    %}
    {% set outputArray = outputArray|merge([postOutput]) %}
{% endfor %}

{{ outputArray|json_encode(constant('JSON_PRETTY_PRINT'))|raw }}

</code></pre>

<p>I dropped that into the root directory Sculpin uses for generating
my site, named it <code>feed.json.twig</code> and now I had a JSON-based feed
for the site.</p>

<p>Now, the GitHub action. This would go in <code>.github/workflows/send-webmention.yaml</code>
for my repo that I am using for the page.</p>

<pre><code>name: Send Webmentions

on: push

jobs:
  send:
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    steps:

      - name: Send Webmentions
        env:
          GITHUB_TOKEN: $
          URL: $
        run: |
          NEW=$(curl --silent $URL | jq -r first.uri)

          curl -X POST https://webmention.app/check?url="https://grumpy.learning.com$NEW"

          curl -H "Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded" --request POST \
          -d source="https://grumpy-learning.com$NEW" \
          -d target="https://brid.gy/publish/twitter" \
          "https://brid.gy/publish/webmention"

          curl -H "Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded" --request POST \
          -d source="https://grumpy-learning.com$NEW" \
          -d target="https://brid.gy/publish/mastodon" \
          "https://brid.gy/publish/webmention"
</code></pre>

<p>The <a href="https://gist.github.com/dianoetic/b45466a7c04fa47cf80905b182dbda3c">original instructions</a> recommended
putting the JSON feed details into a secret and then referencing it inside the action.
I am not sure it matters that much but stuck with it.</p>

<p>So, the next thing is that it grabs the feed using <a href="https://curl.se">cURL</a> and grabs what
it thinks is the latest post (the first one in the feed) and then proceeds to use
<a href="https://webmention.app">webmention.app</a> and Brid.gy to syndicate my content by sharing
the post title and linking to it).</p>

<p>So far it is working well and if you came across this post via my social media microblogging (I
sound so pretentious when I say it out loud) then it clearly worked.</p>

<p>I think my takeway from this is that gluing things together so your existing blog
can syndicate content to a variety of platforms. If you're looking to have more control over
the things you share online, I highly recommend looking into the IndieWeb. I hope this post helps!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Federating Yourself]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2022/11/12/federating-yourself/"/>
            <updated>2022-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2022/11/12/federating-yourself/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I write this blog post, Twitter is convulsing as it's new
owner Elon Musk is trying to treat a huge cruise ship like
it's a jetski. Having cut a ton of staff and literally workshopping
ideas in public, it's not going well.</p>

<p>I have ignored blogging and some other interactions as Twitter made
it so easy to share those little thoughts and I also became reliant
on a curated feed to find stuff I was interested in. Along the way
I ran into the idea of the <a href="https://indieweb.org/">IndieWeb</a>.</p>

<p>I have made a non-trivial amount of money off selling my <a href="https://leanpub.com/u/chartjes">books</a>
and have dabbled in paid courses and workshops. So it made a lot of
sense to me to check out this <a href="https://indiewebify.me">guide to joining the IndieWeb</a>
and learn about <a href="https://microformats.org">microformats</a>, <a href="http://webmention.org/">Webmentions</a>
and start really leaning into POSSEing (Publish on my Own Site, Syndicate Elsewhere)
my stuff.</p>

<p>This is the first blog post that (if I have set up things correctly at my end) that
will be syndicated out to other platforms.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>