<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Grumpy Learning]]></title>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/categories/notes.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/"/>
    <updated>2024-11-22T22:24:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/</id>
            <author>
            <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                    </author>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes -- November 22, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/11/22/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/11/22/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back on the notes grind...</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>ZiffDavis Shopping is getting close to our Super Bowl -- Black Friday and Cyber Monday</li>
<li>wrote a PHP CLI tool that will mimic an existing Python job and emit events for updating reward budgets as we pay folks out</li>
<li>diving deeper into Laravel Nova actions and creating code for doing CSV exports of selected Eloquent models</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I got asked a question on social media about how to handle things when you
come onto a team as Staff-level engineer and getting them
to commit to making things more maintainable.</p>

<p>I could do a whole talk about this, but let me summarize a few points.</p>

<p>1) talk to the people YOU report TO and get expectations on quality and output
2) ruthlessly enforce those expectations with your team
3) make team understand they are building new habits while delivering what the business wants
4) the path to maintainable code is through being able to write tests for it</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes October 18th, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/18/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/18/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>work has changed to be using scrum...not a fan</li>
<li>learned about how we need to change how we are doing <code>count()</code> queries in <a href="https://nova.laravel.com">Laravel Nova</a></li>
<li>work swtiched from Docker Desktop to <a href="https://podman.io">Podman</a> to avoid the enterprise fees</li>
<li>as we get closer and closer to launching my new transaction processing work, getting into the fringes of triggering events and reacting to them</li>
<li>one talk written and one more to go for <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">CascadiaPHP</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>Is it possible to both be excited and filled with dread at buying a house and moving? We found
a place in the small town where we live (literally a 5 minute drive) and buying
it is conditional on selling our current place in a very tight window (about 5
weeks).</p>

<p>I'm pretty organized these days so the move will likely go smooth but I am going
to spend all winter in a foul move if it falls through.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes October 4th, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/04/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/04/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>See, already got lazy about this. Distracted by stuff
at home and my annual visit to go see the Tigers play
at Comerica Field the last weekend they are at home.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>the IBL regular season is almost over -- 2 weeks to go and my team sits at 73-73</li>
<li>got a foul ball at the Tigers' game -- I whiffed on catching it but it hit me in the gut and dropped to my feet. Awesome souvenir for my buddy's 10yo son</li>
<li>two weeks of fun Commander play, with 20 people coming out each time</li>
<li>finally getting some time to work on my Magic: The Gathering <a href="https://cubecobra.com/cube/overview/grumpycursed">cube</a></li>
<li>some of the last pieces of my work task related to purchase validation are getting built</li>
<li>demo of some other features built by the rest of the team went well</li>
<li>pool is now closed as we settle in for a Southwestern Ontario fall</li>
<li>started working on my slides for my two talks at <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">CascadiaPHP 2024</a></li>
<li>house hunting has started as we look for something without a pool (I'm the only one really using it, plus with our youngest having epilepsy there is significant risk to her swimming) and move from a two-story home to a bungalow</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>Nothing really other than my absences from home make me realize what
a creature of routine I have become over the years. Even an overnight
visit feels like it was super long. Weird sensation for sure.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes September 13th, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/13/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/13/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Shout out to <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason_Voorhees">Jason Voorhees</a>
on his special day.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>no IBL games this week as we had a real week off -- will be playing some games this upcoming Sunday</li>
<li>amazing turnout for Commander night -- 24 people</li>
<li>put my favourite deck back together (<a href="https://archidekt.com/decks/9190742/grolnok_v3">Grolnok Turbo Self-Mill</a> and remembered how that deck quickly becomes the archenemy of the table as it is fast and consistent</li>
<li>finally got my transaction audit work merged into the main branch at work</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>This upcoming Monday I am going to a meeting with my mother
at the nursing home where my father lives to go over his
care. Some of you might know that my father is suffering 
from dementia for about a decade now and has been in
this home for 2-1/2 years now.</p>

<p>I try and see him whenever I go back to visit my mom and
for the most part the visits have gone okay. He seems to
almost always remember that he has a son and the last
few visits he always recognizes my mother. Conversations
are hard because he doesn't remember anything and I don't
have enough things on my phone to really distract him. My
mother often brings an iPad with her and shows him videos
or pictures of things.</p>

<p>The whole thing is really, really sad. I have no idea if
I will dodge the same fate as him.</p>

<p>I think the thing that bothers me the most is that while
he looks like and sounds like my Dad, it's not. He never
remembers I have kids or that I am married. I haven't
heard him talk about my older sister at all.</p>

<p>I just wish he was able to experience that his son truly
made it and has a nice comfortable life.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes September 7th, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/07/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/07/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games</li>
<li>has my usual Commander Night at my local gaming store</li>
<li>the transaction audit log work is proving to be a slog</li>
<li>discovered that you can configure PhpStorm's <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/help/phpstorm/using-product-as-the-vim-editor.html">IdeaVim</a> plugin via a <code>.ideavimrc</code> file to make the experience a little more Vim-like. Shoutout to Eric Johnson from <a href="https://www.phparch.com">php|architect</a> for showing me how</li>
<li>flights booked for going to <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">CascadiaPHP</a> at the end of October</li>
<li>a testing scenario for the transaction audit log revealed that my <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chain-of-responsibility_pattern">chain-of-responsibility</a> implementation for a series of validators for a rebate offer was just wrong, so off I went fixing it by switching to using <a href="https://laravel.com/docs/11.x/helpers#pipeline">pipelines in laravel</a>. Don't worry, all the individual validators have tests</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I was going to do a longer piece on how I felt I was at
a "crossroads" with my IDE choices. I know it sounds like
dramatic whining.</p>

<p>I have been a Vim/NeoVim user for a long time. The HJKL
muscle memory is burned in and I expect almost everything
I use to be modal. For everything other than PHP, I use
NeoVim.</p>

<p>But lately I am feeling...resentful about how all the tools
I have started to rely on seem to have "becoming a subscription"
as an aspirational goal. My renewal for my PhpStorm subscription
is coming up and I am trying to decide if I can just not renew
it and go back to NeoVim.</p>

<p>The ONLY reason I switched to using PhpStorm was because it
made some other aspects of development work easier:</p>

<ul>
<li>easily get Xdebug working and a slick interface for it</li>
<li>same with doing development work with Dockerized development environments</li>
<li>make it easy to run my tests inside that Dockerized environments</li>
<li>"intellesense" support baked in</li>
</ul>

<p>There are other editors I have looked at -- <a href="https://helix-editor.com">Helix</a>,
<a href="https://zed.dev">Zed</a>, and even the dreaded Emacs. Other than Emacs,
the newer editors fall down when we get to the plugin and
customization phage of creating a development environment.</p>

<p>From a pragmatic side, sticking with NeoVim due to intimate 
familiarity with it's modal nature and basic keybindings
makes the most sense.</p>

<p>Emacs is an interesting choice because it is basically like
NeoVim in that it has a long, rich history and is incredibly
configurable. But learning a whole new series of keybindings?
Seems very daunting.</p>

<p>Helix seems nice. Xdebug support appears to be very rough to
get working. Have to have it for my PHP work, sorry. No idea
if it can be made to support Xdebug running inside a Docker
container. Again, need to check back later.</p>

<p>Zed -- no support for Xdebug. I'll check back later when
they maybe bake in Debug Anywhere Protocol support.</p>

<p>So time to see if I can get NeoVim to give me the extra
tooling that PhpStorm currently offers.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes September 1st, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/01/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/09/01/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games, where we continue to hover around the .500 mark</li>
<li>double dose of Magic: The Gathering this week -- played both my <a href="https://cubecobra.com/cube/overview/grumpycursed">cursed cube</a> and <a href="https://pdhhomebase.com">pauper commander</a></li>
<li>implemented some transaction audit logging at work -- test cases as expected</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I read an excelled blog post from Steven Yegge where he talked about how
he felt it was a <a href="https://sourcegraph.com/blog/the-death-of-the-junior-developer?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email">bad time to be a junior developer</a>,
which dovetails nicely into me needing to deliver a talk at the end
of October to the audience at <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">Cascadia PHP</a>
about how a hater like me uses LLM's.</p>

<p>I don't want to spoil the main points of the talk, but it is fair
to say I already use some LLM's (Apple iPhone already has stuff
in it) and I have occasionally turned it on when trying to refactor
some code.</p>

<p>Can't ignore all the grifters and rent-seekers hanging around
the industry and it does feel like a bubble is gonna pop.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes August 25, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/25/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/25/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A little late this week.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games, where we continue to hover around the .500 mark</li>
<li>did a lot of work with <a href="https://nova.laravel.com">Nova</a> to build a dashboard for auditing transactions as they flow through our verification system</li>
<li>a fun Thursday of Magic: The Gathering playing commander</li>
<li>stomach still not great</li>
<li>played Doomlings and our 6+ year <a href="http://www.apocalypse-world.com">Apocalypse World</a> game</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I tried out Emacs this week at work for a little bit each
day and it is just different enough from what my Vim
muscle memory wants that I have put it on hold.</p>

<p>Instead, I am concentrating on building new muscle memory
to use <a href="https://precondition.github.io/home-row-mods">home row mods</a>
to reduce how often I have to reach for the Shift and Alt keys.
It's jarring to actually feel the pause as I stop to use the
home row "shift".</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes August 16, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/16/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/16/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games via instructions (team managers create documents for how they want their team to be run)</li>
<li>finished writing all the tests for additional scenarios for the transaction processing job</li>
<li>no Magic: The Gathering this week as Commander night was my 26th wedding anniversary</li>
<li>stomach is feeling a little better -- I wonder if the ache I feel is because of damage all that stomach acid has done :(</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I came across a blog post from a developer about <a href="https://protesilaos.com/codelog/2019-08-11-why-emacs-switch/">why they switched to Emacs</a>
and it make me wonder if I should try switching from Vim to Emacs. Again.</p>

<p>I tried it once before but couldn't duplicate my developer work flow.
I feel like the combination of <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a> + <a href="http://xahlee.info/emacs/misc/xah-fly-keys.html">xah-fly-keys</a> is
a great start since it would give me a similar modal editing experience
that I expect in my editor.</p>

<p>Of course, the bigger issue is that I would have to set things up twice
-- once on my work computer that ZiffDavis gave me and once on my own
machine. I also pay for a license for <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">PhpStorm</a>
and it is up for renewal soon.</p>

<p>Good to keep learning things. I've been using Vim so long that navigating via H-J-K-L
is deeply embedded in muscle memory. I have noticed over the years that I don't really
do much "web surfing" on my laptop -- I use my iPhone for that so having Vim bindings
for my browser doesn't make mush sense.</p>

<h2 id="everything-else">Everything Else</h2>

<ul>
<li>going to be playing <a href="https://doomlings.com">Doomlings</a> this weekend as part of my monthly board gaming session</li>
<li>if you are interested in ergonomic keyboards I would check out the Glove80 from <a href="https://www.moergo.com">moergo</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes August 9, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/08/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/08/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trying out something new to capture all the stuff giong on
in my life with the idea of <a href="https://tracydurnell.com/2024/07/30/using-personal-weeknotes-as-a-tool-for-attention/">weeknotes</a>.
It's not that my ego think you want to know about all aspects
of life but I am starting to feel like I lose track of some
of the more ephemeral parts of my life in what I discover
online.</p>

<p>Plus, I do think it is valuable for other developers with
less experience getting paid to write code to see what it
is actually like to be a senior developer. It's definitely
not Magical Christmas Land but it's not "move this button
to the left and implement this AI chatbot plugin" either.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games both on Sunday afternoon and Monday night</li>
<li>spent Monday afternoon checking out some different parks in London, ON with my wife (we like to do low-to-medium intensity hikes)</li>
<li>started working on adding a series of test scenarios to my work at ZiffDavis Shopping for a transaction processing job</li>
<li>doing reviews of PR's involving Python at work is an interesting challenge as I know just enough to have a basic understanding but not enough to catch edge cases as the moment</li>
<li>played <a href="https://mtgcommander.net">Commander</a> as usual on Thursday night</li>
<li>added deck lists to <a href="https://archidekt.com">Archidekt</a> for ones I am playing</li>
<li>continue to alter my eating habits while I deal with stomach issues (hopefully not becoming <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/gerd/symptoms-causes/syc-20361940">GERD</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I keep coming back to the phrase "post-testing software development world" and are finally organizing these thoughts.
I should probably do a series of blog posts here about it. It's clear that things have definitely shifted in terms
of commitment to testing and with an audience mostly-receptive to the concepts, a shift in how to teach and
advocate for testing seems reasonable.</p>

<h2 id="everything-else">Everything Else</h2>

<ul>
<li>I continue to use the Reminders app on my phone to delay impulse purchase. Steamdeck? Sure, but I barely play the Switch I have</li>
<li>While my <a href="https://www.nurasound.com">Nura</a> ear buds are still in great shape I found a Canadian company called <a href="https://soundsgood.ca">Sounds Good</a> that designs and sells their own line of audio stuff</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>