<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Grumpy Learning]]></title>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/categories/notes.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/"/>
    <updated>2024-08-16T19:24:58+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes August 16, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/16/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/16/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games via instructions (team managers create documents for how they want their team to be run)</li>
<li>finished writing all the tests for additional scenarios for the transaction processing job</li>
<li>no Magic: The Gathering this week as Commander night was my 26th wedding anniversary</li>
<li>stomach is feeling a little better -- I wonder if the ache I feel is because of damage all that stomach acid has done :(</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I came across a blog post from a developer about <a href="https://protesilaos.com/codelog/2019-08-11-why-emacs-switch/">why they switched to Emacs</a>
and it make me wonder if I should try switching from Vim to Emacs. Again.</p>

<p>I tried it once before but couldn't duplicate my developer work flow.
I feel like the combination of <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a> + <a href="http://xahlee.info/emacs/misc/xah-fly-keys.html">xah-fly-keys</a> is
a great start since it would give me a similar modal editing experience
that I expect in my editor.</p>

<p>Of course, the bigger issue is that I would have to set things up twice
-- once on my work computer that ZiffDavis gave me and once on my own
machine. I also pay for a license for <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">PhpStorm</a>
and it is up for renewal soon.</p>

<p>Good to keep learning things. I've been using Vim so long that navigating via H-J-K-L
is deeply embedded in muscle memory. I have noticed over the years that I don't really
do much "web surfing" on my laptop -- I use my iPhone for that so having Vim bindings
for my browser doesn't make mush sense.</p>

<h2 id="everything-else">Everything Else</h2>

<ul>
<li>going to be playing <a href="https://doomlings.com">Doomlings</a> this weekend as part of my monthly board gaming session</li>
<li>if you are interested in ergonomic keyboards I would check out the Glove80 from <a href="https://www.moergo.com">moergo</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weeknotes August 9, 2024]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/08/weeknotes/"/>
            <updated>2024-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/08/08/weeknotes/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trying out something new to capture all the stuff giong on
in my life with the idea of <a href="https://tracydurnell.com/2024/07/30/using-personal-weeknotes-as-a-tool-for-attention/">weeknotes</a>.
It's not that my ego think you want to know about all aspects
of life but I am starting to feel like I lose track of some
of the more ephemeral parts of my life in what I discover
online.</p>

<p>Plus, I do think it is valuable for other developers with
less experience getting paid to write code to see what it
is actually like to be a senior developer. It's definitely
not Magical Christmas Land but it's not "move this button
to the left and implement this AI chatbot plugin" either.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-did">What I Did</h2>

<ul>
<li>played my <a href="https://www.ibl.org">IBL</a> games both on Sunday afternoon and Monday night</li>
<li>spent Monday afternoon checking out some different parks in London, ON with my wife (we like to do low-to-medium intensity hikes)</li>
<li>started working on adding a series of test scenarios to my work at ZiffDavis Shopping for a transaction processing job</li>
<li>doing reviews of PR's involving Python at work is an interesting challenge as I know just enough to have a basic understanding but not enough to catch edge cases as the moment</li>
<li>played <a href="https://mtgcommander.net">Commander</a> as usual on Thursday night</li>
<li>added deck lists to <a href="https://archidekt.com">Archidekt</a> for ones I am playing</li>
<li>continue to alter my eating habits while I deal with stomach issues (hopefully not becoming <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/gerd/symptoms-causes/syc-20361940">GERD</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="longer-threads">Longer Threads</h2>

<p>I keep coming back to the phrase "post-testing software development world" and are finally organizing these thoughts.
I should probably do a series of blog posts here about it. It's clear that things have definitely shifted in terms
of commitment to testing and with an audience mostly-receptive to the concepts, a shift in how to teach and
advocate for testing seems reasonable.</p>

<h2 id="everything-else">Everything Else</h2>

<ul>
<li>I continue to use the Reminders app on my phone to delay impulse purchase. Steamdeck? Sure, but I barely play the Switch I have</li>
<li>While my <a href="https://www.nurasound.com">Nura</a> ear buds are still in great shape I found a Canadian company called <a href="https://soundsgood.ca">Sounds Good</a> that designs and sells their own line of audio stuff</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>