<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Grumpy Learning]]></title>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/categories/speaking.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/"/>
    <updated>2024-12-27T15:28:53+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/</id>
            <author>
            <name><![CDATA[Chris Hartjes]]></name>                    </author>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Surviving conferences as a speaker]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/29/surviving-as-a-speaker/"/>
            <updated>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2024/10/29/surviving-as-a-speaker/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just got back from speaking at <a href="https://cascadiaphp.com">CascadiaPHP</a>
and wanted to share some thoughts about how I approach going to conferences
as a speaker and maybe you will find it helpful too.</p>

<h3 id="you-are-playing-a-dual-role">You are playing a dual role</h3>

<p>I have been going to conferences since 2003 and speaking at them since 2005.
That is a very long time, spanning the vast majority of my professional
career. Most of my energy and attention are devoted to making sure that
I deliver the best talk I can at the time I give it.</p>

<p>I also need to show other attendees that I still have things to learn so
I make sure to go to other talks.</p>

<p>I understand that for some folks time pressures are such that they come in,
give a talk, and then immediately leave. I am not a fan of that approach and
would never do it -- I would just simply decline the opportunity. But for
many events they are marketed as an opportunity to get access to some of
the most knowledgeable people in your programming community. So I feel
you should give back by making sure to talk to other people, make some
new community friends, and encourage people to continue to attend these
events.</p>

<p>So make sure to support your other speakers by attending their talks. I
know I missed some talks at CascadiaPHP because I was not handling
the 3-hour time difference well and I was catching up with some old friends
during other talks. I did get to some talks of things I was interested in
and that is really what we are here for.</p>

<h3 id="know-your-material">Know your material</h3>

<p>I will admit that I often don't practice my talks because I make sure I
really know the material before I present. I think I can mostly get away
with this because of my presentation style -- it is kind of like walking
a tightrope.</p>

<p>So even if you can't practice your talk a lot, if you understand the
material really well then a collection of slides that act as the initial
thoughts you want to go over, and then you fill in the rest yourself
makes for really engaging talks.</p>

<h3 id="answer-questions-and-ask-questions">Answer questions and ask questions</h3>

<p>This can be hard for people who suffer from "imposter syndrome". My joke
about this is that my ego is too large for me to think I am an imposter,
but the truth is I am highly confident that I can figure out how to do
just about anything. The key to pulling that off is to understand when
you don't know something and then figure out who you can ask for help.</p>

<p>In the context of a conference, I try to do talks that question the
way some things are, present my point of view, and then ask the audience
to consider what I've told them. You don't have to agree with everything
I say (talks that like that are boring) but I do actually change my mind
over time and with experience. So try and get your audience thinking
and wanting to ask questions.</p>

<p>Conversely, if you are watching someone else's talk and don't understand
what is going on, ask them a question if you can. I generally ask people
to save their questions for the end of my talks but feel free to go with
whatever feels right for you.</p>

<p>A great example of this is the topic of <a href="https://phpstan.org/blog/generics-by-examples">generics in PHP</a>. I have never
used them and have not been able to figure out on my own why they might
be useful to me. There was a talk about <a href="https://phpstan.org">PHPStan</a>
and they mentioned generics. I didn't ask the speaker about them as
I got to the end so instead I asked some of my fellow developers if
they could explain to me why I should care about them. They provided
me with some insights into when and where I might want to use them
so next time I am building something that could benefit from Generics,
I will give it a try.</p>

<p>If I hadn't asked, a question I probably would still be thinking they were something
I would not have to worry about.</p>

<h3 id="take-care-of-yourself">Take care of yourself</h3>

<p>Make sure to eat.</p>

<p>Make sure to get proper amounts of rest.</p>

<p>Don't treat the conference like it's an excuse to cut loose and abuse yourself.</p>

<p>I don't want to say things like "be a professional" because that on it's own
is really insulting. Instead, be respectful towards yourself.</p>

<h3 id="have-your-slides-done-ahead-of-time">Have your slides done ahead of time</h3>

<p>There is the trope of folks doing their slides at the last minute. In almost
every case I have my slides all done before I come to the event, This time
I ended up needing to devote the time I would've spent on slides for one
of my presentations doing stuff around my house getting it ready to be sold.
I ended up finishing the slides in my hotel room during a block of talks
that I did not find interesting enough to attend.</p>

<h3 id="sometimes-the-talk-just-doesn%27t-work">Sometimes the talk just doesn't work</h3>

<p>This final one is tricky. Sometimes, a talk just doesn't resonate with the
audience. You miscalculated how much time you had. You wanted to talk theory
but the audience was expecting examples. You only prepared 30 minutes when
the slot was an hour. It was the first time you gave the talk. It happens.
I view them as teachable lessons about what the audience is expecting from
you, which becomes even more important if you are lucky enough to have
a long enough speaking career where there are expectations that you are
going to be a certain way.</p>

<p>We can all learn from our challenges -- failing to do so is the real issue.</p>

<h3 id="you-made-it%21">You made it!</h3>

<p>If you want to an event and spoke, congratulations! Now try and make the
experience for your audience and yourself just a little bit better next time.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talks with secret topics]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2023/12/29/secret-talks/"/>
            <updated>2023-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2023/12/29/secret-talks/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="talks-with-secret-topics">Talks With Secret Topics</h1>

<p>I've been speaking at conferences since 2005. Yes, that is
a ridiculously long time. While these talks have mostly been
about testing practices, I enjoy creating talks that actually
have a secret topic in them. It's usually related to the main
topic, but given I usually have 60 minutes to fill I feel like
I need to give the attendees a glimpse into how my grumpy mind
works.</p>

<p>Many of my testing talks end up covering one of more "secret
topics":</p>

<ul>
<li>defensive coding styles</li>
<li>third party tools to apply consistency</li>
<li>design patterns</li>
<li>how luck is just really skill and opportunity intersecting</li>
</ul>

<p>On the one hand, I have a captive audience forced to listen to me.
On the other hand, I do like to be entertaining and informative.
Choosing this "secret topic" style allows me to embrace what
I feel are the good parts of me:</p>

<ul>
<li>loves to talk</li>
<li>has seen so so many good and bad things in his career</li>
<li>wants to help people learn faster than I did with less suffering</li>
</ul>

<p>I will be speaking at <a href="https://tek.phparch.com">php[tek] 2024</a> in
Chicago at the end of April. After speaking at LonghornPHP in 2022
I had decided to no longer do testing talks. I've been doing them
since 2005. 18 years is enough. Please. No more.</p>

<p>I got selected to give two talks, none of which are testing related.
I want to share what those talks are probably going to look like. I
don't have them written yet but I have the outline rattling around
inside my head and it will get turned into slides and (in a newer twist)
some live coding to go with it.</p>

<h2 id="cqrs-talk...-that-is-really-about-web-site-architectures">CQRS talk... that is really about web site architectures</h2>

<p>My first talk is "Break loose from CRUD - use CQRS" where I will show
how I refactored a legacy PHP application that was a mess using the
Command Query Responsibility Segregation pattern.</p>

<p>In order to understand why we have more options that the "traditional"
Create Read Update Delete (or CRUD) pattern that ties our implementation
to database-related actions, I plan on doing a brief history of architectures
that can be used with web applications. I think a lot of folks simply
are not aware of the different options available to them due the domination
of modern PHP web application frameworks by a few <a href="https://laravel.com">big</a>
<a href="https://symfony.com">players</a>.</p>

<p>I chose CQRS for a project because it had been related to another topic
(<a href="https://martinfowler.com/eaaDev/EventSourcing.html">event sourcing</a>]
that other much-smarter programmers than me had been talking about.</p>

<h2 id="neovim-as-php-ide-talk...that-is-really-about-mastering-tools">NeoVim-as-PHP-IDE talk...that is really about mastering tools</h2>

<p>My second talk is about my <a href="https://neovim.io">NeoVim</a> setup for doing
PHP work. I also use <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">PhpStorm</a> a lot
for my PHP work, but it's good to have options.</p>

<p>I learned how to use Vim almost 20 years ago but dabbled constantly with
other editors. Some of it was tribalism, some of it was my restlessness
with the status quo. I've used Vim/NeoVim for so long that my muscle
memory is strong enough to ruin working inside tools that do not support
Vim bindings or modal editing.</p>

<p>NeoVim being completely customizable forces you down the road of thoughtful
customization -- since so many things are possible, and not constrained
by NeoVim itself, you are responsible for figuring out what you want your
IDE experience to be like.</p>

<p>So this talk will cover my own path to selecting and mastering tools.
Understanding the limitations of something is the best way to push it
in the direction you really want it to go.</p>

<h2 id="secret-talks-require-confidence">Secret Talks Require Confidence</h2>

<p>It's no secret that I carry myself with a lot of confidence -- the whole
Grumpy Learning brand would not have worked without it. When you also
decide to create secret talks, you need to have the ability to tell a
story and weave different elements together to constantly reinforce
the overall message.</p>

<p>I don't think this technique is for everybody -- it requires being
comfortable with the idea that there is a lot of background information
that is relevant to the topic your talk is supposed to be covering.</p>

<p>At this point, I don't think I could build talks any other way and still
be true to myself.</p>

<p>I hope to see you at tek2024!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>