<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Grumpy Learning]]></title>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/categories/speaking.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/"/>
    <updated>2024-02-17T21:47:22+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talks with secret topics]]></title>
            <link href="https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2023/12/29/secret-talks/"/>
            <updated>2023-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://grumpy-learning.com/blog/2023/12/29/secret-talks/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="talks-with-secret-topics">Talks With Secret Topics</h1>

<p>I've been speaking at conferences since 2005. Yes, that is
a ridiculously long time. While these talks have mostly been
about testing practices, I enjoy creating talks that actually
have a secret topic in them. It's usually related to the main
topic, but given I usually have 60 minutes to fill I feel like
I need to give the attendees a glimpse into how my grumpy mind
works.</p>

<p>Many of my testing talks end up covering one of more "secret
topics":</p>

<ul>
<li>defensive coding styles</li>
<li>third party tools to apply consistency</li>
<li>design patterns</li>
<li>how luck is just really skill and opportunity intersecting</li>
</ul>

<p>On the one hand, I have a captive audience forced to listen to me.
On the other hand, I do like to be entertaining and informative.
Choosing this "secret topic" style allows me to embrace what
I feel are the good parts of me:</p>

<ul>
<li>loves to talk</li>
<li>has seen so so many good and bad things in his career</li>
<li>wants to help people learn faster than I did with less suffering</li>
</ul>

<p>I will be speaking at <a href="https://tek.phparch.com">php[tek] 2024</a> in
Chicago at the end of April. After speaking at LonghornPHP in 2022
I had decided to no longer do testing talks. I've been doing them
since 2005. 18 years is enough. Please. No more.</p>

<p>I got selected to give two talks, none of which are testing related.
I want to share what those talks are probably going to look like. I
don't have them written yet but I have the outline rattling around
inside my head and it will get turned into slides and (in a newer twist)
some live coding to go with it.</p>

<h2 id="cqrs-talk...-that-is-really-about-web-site-architectures">CQRS talk... that is really about web site architectures</h2>

<p>My first talk is "Break loose from CRUD - use CQRS" where I will show
how I refactored a legacy PHP application that was a mess using the
Command Query Responsibility Segregation pattern.</p>

<p>In order to understand why we have more options that the "traditional"
Create Read Update Delete (or CRUD) pattern that ties our implementation
to database-related actions, I plan on doing a brief history of architectures
that can be used with web applications. I think a lot of folks simply
are not aware of the different options available to them due the domination
of modern PHP web application frameworks by a few <a href="https://laravel.com">big</a>
<a href="https://symfony.com">players</a>.</p>

<p>I chose CQRS for a project because it had been related to another topic
(<a href="https://martinfowler.com/eaaDev/EventSourcing.html">event sourcing</a>]
that other much-smarter programmers than me had been talking about.</p>

<h2 id="neovim-as-php-ide-talk...that-is-really-about-mastering-tools">NeoVim-as-PHP-IDE talk...that is really about mastering tools</h2>

<p>My second talk is about my <a href="https://neovim.io">NeoVim</a> setup for doing
PHP work. I also use <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">PhpStorm</a> a lot
for my PHP work, but it's good to have options.</p>

<p>I learned how to use Vim almost 20 years ago but dabbled constantly with
other editors. Some of it was tribalism, some of it was my restlessness
with the status quo. I've used Vim/NeoVim for so long that my muscle
memory is strong enough to ruin working inside tools that do not support
Vim bindings or modal editing.</p>

<p>NeoVim being completely customizable forces you down the road of thoughtful
customization -- since so many things are possible, and not constrained
by NeoVim itself, you are responsible for figuring out what you want your
IDE experience to be like.</p>

<p>So this talk will cover my own path to selecting and mastering tools.
Understanding the limitations of something is the best way to push it
in the direction you really want it to go.</p>

<h2 id="secret-talks-require-confidence">Secret Talks Require Confidence</h2>

<p>It's no secret that I carry myself with a lot of confidence -- the whole
Grumpy Learning brand would not have worked without it. When you also
decide to create secret talks, you need to have the ability to tell a
story and weave different elements together to constantly reinforce
the overall message.</p>

<p>I don't think this technique is for everybody -- it requires being
comfortable with the idea that there is a lot of background information
that is relevant to the topic your talk is supposed to be covering.</p>

<p>At this point, I don't think I could build talks any other way and still
be true to myself.</p>

<p>I hope to see you at tek2024!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>